<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>Latest version of this paper and the code used to produce it are available from http://www.opentorah.org/.</para>

  <para>In the "Laws of Sanctification of the Moon", Rambam gives algorithmic description of two
    calendars: fixed ("arithmetic") and observational ("astronomical"). Both calendars are described in a form ready
    to be implemented, but the reasons for the calculation steps - especially for the astronomical calendar - are not
    always given: what are the models - and the formulae resulting from them - that reproduce the numbers?
    Sometimes Rambam describes the models, so only the formulae need to be reconstructed; sometimes the models are not
    described, so both the models and the formulae need to be reconstructed.</para>

  <para>Goals of this paper are:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>reconstruct models that Rambam uses from the Rambam's text</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>describe the models with diagrams and formulae</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>reconstruct actual parameters of the models from the numbers given by Rambam</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>identify misprints in the traditional editions</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>analyze correspondence with the fixed calendar</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>verify Rambam's tables and rounding decisions against his models</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>analyze impact of various misprints on the sighting calculations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Verify consistency of Rambam's numbers.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Translate relevant chapters of Rambam into English. The translation does not have to be literal;
        literal translations are already available (<biblioref linkend="Yale"/>, <biblioref linkend="Touger"/>). The
        goal of our translation is to make the text complete and accessible for collaboration by people not proficient
        enough in Hebrew.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>see how Rambam's calculations of the moon visibility compare to the current models</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>Approximate timeline of the project:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>In 1984, The Rebbe instructed Jews to learn Rambam every day. As a result, in 1991 I encountered calendar
          chapters of Rambam, decided to reconstruct the models behind the calculations described in them, and discovered
          mistakes in the text of one of the laws (15:6). The results were published in "Notices of Temimim and Anash", a
          weekly of the central Lubavicher Yeshiva 770. Some of the readers were appalled that someone dares to correct the
          text of Rambam! My point was that the text as published contains mistakes that need to be corrected. Indeed,
          Frenkel edition [<biblioref linkend="Frenkel"/>], that was already published at the time, corrects all of the
          mistakes I did. In fact, they were already corrected by Hazon Ish in his commentary on Rambam [<biblioref
            linkend="HazonIsh"/>] - but I did not know it then.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2008: I acquired a pile of books on the subject and started looking into it; I also experimented with
          various ways of publishing the work on the web.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2009: coded some of the algorithms to look into the rumors the dates of
          <ulink url="http://dub.podval.org/2019/07/18/sanctification-of-the-sun.html">Birkhat HaHamah</ulink> that were
          circulating then.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2013: code converted to Scala.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2017-2018: split-file encoding of the family polymorphism and current representation of the dates and angles
          were implemented in the supporting code.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>2018-2019: generation of reading and learning schedules was added to the code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

  <para>I want to acknowledge people who contributed to the content of this work - and to the fact of its existence ;)
    If your name should be on this list but isn't, please forgive me: the omission is not intentional.
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><personname><firstname>Mordechai</firstname><surname>Goldin</surname></personname> - for providing office
        space and computer equipment when I, as a Yeshiva student, had neither;</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        <personname><firstname>Ilia</firstname><surname>Pomansky</surname></personname> - for encouraging this work at
        the early stages, in 1991;</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        my wife Nina - for listening to my wild ideas, for her patience, and for help with
        math;
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>
        my daughter Menucha Rochel - for assistance with the translation;
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Rabbi Michael Koretz -
        for stimulating discussions during our visit to Israel in 2005,
        encouragement, and extensive research into customs of Torah/Haftarah reading;</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Dr. Michael Partensky - for encouragement and advise;</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Dr. Peter Ofman - for asking questions that prodded me to revive this project in 2011, after years of hiatus;</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Aron Matskin - for a discussion during his visit on Rosh Chodesh Mar Cheshvan 5772;</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Rabbi Chaim Prus - for causing me
        to investigate which number does the year of Creation has - 0 or 1;</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</preface>
