<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="KH13">
  <title>Chapter 13</title>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-1" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 1</title>
    
    <para>If you want to find out true position of the Sun for any day that you want, first calculate its mean position for that day
      the way we explained, and calculate position of the Sun's apogee. Subtract position of the Sun's apogee from the Sun's mean position;
      what is left is called <glossterm>maslul of the Sun</glossterm>.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-2" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 2</title>
    <para>See how many degrees is the maslul of the Sun;
      if maslul was less than one hundred and eighty degrees, subtract parallax correction from the position of the mean Sun;
      if maslul was more than one hundred and eighty degrees up to three hundred and sixty, add parallax correction to the position of the mean Sun;
      that what it is after you add to it or subtract from it is the true position.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-3" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 3</title>
    <para>Know that if maslul is exactly one hundred and eighty or exactly three hundred and sixty, it doesn't have parallax correction;
      rather, the mean position is the true position</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-4" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 4</title>
    <para>And what is the value of the parallax correction?
      If maslul will be ten degrees, its parallax correction will be twenty seconds;
      and if it will be twenty degrees, its parallax correction will be fourty minutes;
      and if it will be thirty degrees, its parallax correction will be fifty eight minutes;
      and if it will be fourty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fifteen minutes;
      and if it will be fifty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and twenty nine minutes;
      and if it will be sixty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fourty one minutes;
      and if it will be seventy degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fifty one minutes;
      and if it will be eighty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fifty seven minutes;
      and if it will be ninety degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fifty nine minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fifty eight minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and ten degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fifty three minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and twenty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and fourty five minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and thirty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and thirty three minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and forty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and nineteen minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and fifty degrees, its parallax correction will be one degree and one minute;
      and if it will be one hundred and sizty degrees, its parallax correction will be fourty two minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and seventy degrees, its parallax correction will be twenty one minutes;
      and if it will be one hundred and eighty degrees exactly, it doesn't have parallax correction, as we explained,
      rather Sun's mean position is its true position.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-5" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 5</title>
    <para>If maslul was more that one hundred and eighty degrees, subtract it from three hundred and sixty degrees and find out its parallax correction.
      For example, if maslul was two hundred degrees, subtract it from three hundred and suxty, and one hundred and sixty degrees will be left.
      And we already made known that parallax correction for one hundred and sixty degrees is fourty two minutes,
      and so is the parallax correction for two hundred - fourty two minutes.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-6" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 6</title>
    <para>Also, if the maslul was three hindred degrees, subtract it from three hundred and sixty - and sixty will remain.
    And you already know that parallax correction for sixty degrees [is] one degree and fouty one minutes,
    and so is the parallax correction for three hundred degrees. And the same way - for every number.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-7" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 7</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-8" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 8</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-9" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 9</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-10" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 10</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="KH13-11" role="NotInToc">
    <title>Law 11</title>
    <para>TODO</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
