<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="kh-6-sicho">
  <!-- TODO SIE translation is available as chapter 4 of-->
  <!--https://www.sie.org/templates/sie/article_cdo/aid/2518606/jewish/Shabbos-Parshas-Chukas-1st-Day-of-Rosh-Chodesh-Tammuz-5744-1984.htm-->

  <para>As usual, we shall analyze a point in the daily portion of Rambam’s
    Mishneh Torah — chapters 9-11 of the Laws of Sanctification of the New Moon.
    Earlier, Rambam described the method of reckoning to determine when will be
    the birth of the new moon (chapter 6). Basically, the period of time between
    the births of each new moon is a fixed period: 29 days, 12 hours (1 day = 24
    hours) and 793 parts (1 hour = 1080 parts). If the exact time of the birth
    of any new moon is known, one need merely add the above figure to that time
    to know when will be the birth of the next new moon. Adding this figure again
    will give the time of the birth of the new moon after that, and so forth. To
    make the calculations easier, Rambam advises a simple method. We are
    interested only in knowing on which day of the week and at which time of
    day the new moon will be born. If one subtracts round weeks from the above
    figure, one will be left with 1 day, 12 hours and 793 parts.
    [I.e., 29 days, 12 hours, 793 parts minus 28 days (4 whole weeks) = 1 day,
    12 hours, 793 parts.] This is termed the “remainder of the lunar month.”
    Adding this figure to the time of birth of a new moon will give the day of
    the week, the hour, and the number of parts of the hour at which the next
    birth of the new moon will occur.</para>

  <para>The 24 hour day is divided into two parts — “day” proper (i.e. daytime) and
    night, each of 12 hours duration, with the night preceding the day. The night
    is considered to start from 6 p.m. and extends until 6 a.m.; day from 6 a.m.
    until 6 p.m.</para>

  <para>Rambam then gives an example (6:7). The birth of the new moon for the month
    of Nissan was Sunday, at the fifth hour of the “day,” and 107th part of the
    hour (i.e. Sunday, at 11 a.m. and 107/1080 of the hour). Adding the “remainder
    of the lunar month” — 1 day, 12 hours, 793 parts — gives the birth of the new
    moon for the next month (Iyar) as Monday night, at the fifth hour and 900th
    part of the night (i.e. Monday night, at 11 p.m. and 900/1080 of the hour).</para>

  <para>Rambam wrote Mishneh Torah with the utmost precision. We can therefore assume
    that the example he chose as the given date for the birth of a new moon — for
    Nissan, Sunday, at the fifth hour and 107th part of that hour — has significance.</para>

  <para>Similarly, we find in today’s portion of Mishneh Torah (chapter 11, halachah
    16 of the Laws of the Sanctification of the New Moon) that Rambam gives a date
    which he says he will use as the basic starting point for all calculations to
    know where exactly the moon will be at any given time. That date is “The
    beginning of the eve of Thursday (i.e. Wednesday 6:00 p.m.), the third of
    Nissan .., of the year 4938 from creation.”</para>

  <para>Again, the question is: What is the reason for choosing this date specifically.
    Indeed, R. Levi Ibin Chaviv, in his commentary on Rambam, says: “I question why
    the Rav (i.e. Rambam) used the third of the month as his basic starting point; it
    would have been proper to use the first of the month.” However, R. Levi Ibin
    Chaviv makes no comment on Rambam’s choice of the example quoted previously
    (Sunday during the day at the fifth hour and 107th part of the hour).</para>

  <para>The “Pirush” (a commentary on Rambam’s “Laws of Sanctification of the New Moon”)
    notes that the date chosen by Rambam as his basic starting point (in chapter 11,
    halachah 16) was concurrent to when Rambam lived. He writes “Know that this basic
    date from which the sage (i.e. Rambam) started is far removed from our times
    (i.e. the times of the “Pirush”). We therefore must set another basic date from
    which we will start [to make calculations]...”</para>

  <para>We can posit that the same is true of the date given by Rambam as an example of
    the birth of a new moon (in chapter 6, halachah 7) — for the month of Nissan,
    Sunday, at the fifth hour of the day, and at the 107th part of the hour. At the
    time Rambam was writing these laws, this was then the actual new moon. Thus
    Rambam chose as his example the birth of a new moon that happened at the time
    he was writing these laws, and not a new moon from earlier or from the future.</para>

  <para>But not all is clear: Earlier, at the beginning of today’s portion (chapter 9,
    halachah 5), Rambam gives an example of how to find the time of a “tekufah”
    [There are four tekufahs: The tekufahs of Tammuz and Teves — the summer and
    winter solstices (the precise times at which the sun is farthest from the
    equator); and the tekufahs of Nissan and Tishrei — the vernal and autumnal
    equinoxes (the precise times when the sun crosses the equator)]. Again, there
    is an exact length of time between tekufahs. Once the date of one tekufah is
    known, one merely need add the length of time between tekufahs to this date to
    arrive at the precise date of the next tekufah. Rambam then gives an example
    of the calculation necessary to find the time of the tekufah of Nissan of the
    year 4930.</para>

  <para>Now, according to our previous explanation, that Rambam gives examples of the
    time at which he was writing, it follows that Rambam wrote this halachah in
    the year 4930. Yet, as we noted earlier, when setting a basic date from which
    to start calculations, Rambam (in chapter 11, halachah 16) gives the year
    4938 — 8 years later! It is highly improbable that 8 years passed from the
    time Rambam wrote chapter 9 (in which he gave the date as 4930) until he wrote
    chapter 11 (in which he gives the date as 4938) — when Rambam writes that it
    took him 10 years to write the entire Mishneh Torah.</para>

  <para>Moreover, even if Rambam had not given the year 4930 as a date, there would
    still be a problem. It is known that Rambam finished writing Mishneh Torah in
    approximately the year 4940. Rambam wrote Mishneh Torah in order — i.e., the
    laws which are placed earlier were written earlier, and those placed at the
    end of Mishneh Torah were written toward the conclusion of the writing of
    Mishneh Torah. The Laws of Sanctification of the New Moon are near the
    beginning of Mishneh Torah. How is it possible, then, that he wrote the Laws
    of Sanctification of the New Moon in the year 4938, close to the conclusion
    of the writing of Mishneh Torah?</para>

  <para>The Explanation</para>

  <para>After Rambam wrote Mishneh Torah, he checked and corrected it, and then
    re-checked and re-corrected it, etc., such that there were two or three
    different editions. Indeed, Rambam himself wrote to the Sages of Lunel that
    they should correct their copy of his work according to his final edition.</para>

  <para>Naturally, Rambam edited manly those laws which needed correction, not the
    entire manuscript. Even those matters which had to be changed because of
    corrections made by Rambam in other places, Rambam himself did not make these
    changes in his manuscript, but relied on the fact that his readers would
    themselves understand that such corrections naturally follow.</para>

  <para>In our case, Rambam first wrote the Laws of Sanctification of the New Moon in
    the year 4930 (as recorded in chapter 9). The date Rambam gives as the basic
    starting point for calculations — the year 4938 — was the year in which
    Rambam edited and corrected these laws. Hence, when giving a year which to
    use as the basic starting point, he used the year in which he was then, when
    correcting it — 4938, and not the old date in which these laws were originally
    written eight years earlier — 4930.</para>

  <para>In chapter nine, however, no corrections were necessary, and therefore the
    date originally written — 4930 — remained.</para>

  <para>Accordingly, we can say that the time given in the example (in chapter 6,
    halachah 7) for the birth of the new moon — for Nissan, Monday night, at the
    fifth hour and 900th part of the hour — was indeed the time for the birth of
    the new moon for the month of Nissan when Rambam was writing this law.</para>

  <para>There is a lesson to be derived from this, concerning our Sages’ statement,
    “Every day they (Torah and mitzvos) should be new in your eyes as if you were
    commanded about them on that day.” When Rambam edited and corrected a halachah,
    he didn’t edit an old matter that was written 8 years earlier; it was a totally
    new thing, for “every day they should be new in your eyes.” Thus Rambam
    naturally wrote the date of the time he was in now, and not a date of 8 years
    ago! Even if he was working on a manuscript which had the date of 4930 written
    on it, he still wrote the date of the year in which he was now working when he
    edited it — 4938. He wasn’t just correcting something old; it was “new,”
    something which happened “on that day.”</para>

  <para>This teaches every Jew how he should learn Torah. Even when he learns something
    he has learned in the past — even if he has repeated it 101 times (as the Alter
    Rebbe instructs) — his study of it should be such that “every day they should
    be new in your eyes.”</para>
</chapter>