<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
>
  <title>Chapter 15</title>

  <section>
    <title>Law 1</title>

    <para>
      To find true lunar longitude (הירח האמיתי) on a specific day:
      First, calculate mean lunar longitude during observation time of the desired night.
      Also, calculate mean lunar anomaly and mean solar longitude for the same time.
      Then, subtract mean solar longitude from the mean lunar longitude and double the result.
      This value is called <glossterm>doubled distance</glossterm> (מרחק הכפול).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Law 2,3</title>

    <para>
      We already stipulated that all the calculations in these chapters are for one purpose only:
      to know if the moon is visible. And it is not possible for this double distance during the night of
      observation when the moon is indeed visible to be outside of the interval from 5° to 62°.
      It cannot be more - nor less.
      <footnote><para>This is Law 2.</para></footnote>
    </para>

    <para> A correction that depends on the doubled distance is added to the mean lunar
      anomaly, giving  <glossterm>corrected lunar anomaly</glossterm> (מסלול הנכון): </para>

    <informaltable frame="all">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>doubled distance</entry>
            <entry>correction of the mean anomaly</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>~5°</entry>
            <entry>0°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>6°-11°</entry>
            <entry>1°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>12°-18°</entry>
            <entry>2°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>19°-24°</entry>
            <entry>3°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>25°-31°</entry>
            <entry>4°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>32°-38°</entry>
            <entry>5°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>39°-45°</entry>
            <entry>6°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>46°-51°</entry>
            <entry>7°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>52°-59°</entry>
            <entry>8°</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>60°-63°</entry>
            <entry>9°</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Law 4,5,6</title>

    <para xml:id="l15-4"> Then, see how many degrees is corrected lunar anomaly. If it
      is less than 180°, subtract visible anomaly of this corrected anomaly from the
      mean lunar longitude the observation time. And if corrected lunar anomaly is
      more than 180° but less than 360°, add visible anomaly of this corrected anomaly
      to the mean lunar longitude the observation time. And mean lunar longitude after
      you add to it or subtract from it is the
      <glossterm>true lunar longitude at the observation time</glossterm>.
      <footnote><para>This is Law 4.</para></footnote>
    </para>

    <para xml:id="l15-5">
      If the corrected anomaly is 180° or 360°, there is no visible anomaly,
      so mean lunar longitude at observation time is also true longitude.
      <footnote><para>This is Law 5.</para></footnote>
    </para>

    <para xml:id="l15-6">
      What is the value of the visible
      anomaly for a given value of the corrected anomaly?
    </para>

    <!-- TODO
    <xi:include href="mva-original.xml"/>
    -->
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Law 7,8,9:</title>
    <para>
      TODO!!!
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
