<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Chapter 12</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Law 1</title>
    
    <para>The mean rate of movement of the sun in 1 day (that is, 24 hours) is 59′8″.
      It follows that its movement in 10 days is 9°51′23″.
      It also follows that its movement in 100 days is 98°33′53″.
      It also follows that remainder of its movement in 1000 days, after you subtract all [multiples of] 360°
      (as was explained) is 265°38′50″.
      It also follows that the remainder of its movement in 10000 days is 136°28′20″.
    </para>
    
    <para>And in this way you can multiply and calculate its movement for any number [of days] that you want.
      Similarly, if you want to make known to you values of its movement for 2 days, 3, 4 and so on to 10 - do it.
      Similarly, if you want for to have known and ready values of its movement for 20 days, 30, 40 and so on to 100 - do it.
      This is clear and known once you know its movement in 1 day.</para>
    
    <para>And you should have ready and known to you mean movement of the Sun for 29 days and for 354
      (which is the number of days in the lunar year when its months are "regular" (TODO link), and it
      is called "regular year"). The reason is: if you have those movement values ready, this calculations of the
      visibility of the moon will be easy, because there are 29 complete days from the night of observation to
      the night of observation of the following month, and so it is every month: no less than 29 days and no more.
      Since our sole desire in all those calculations is exclusively to determine visibility [of the moon].
      And between the night of sighting of this month and night of sighting of the same month next year there is either
      a regular year or a year and 1 day; and the same every year.
      Mean movement of the Sun in 29 days is 28°35′1″. Its movement in a regular year is 348°55′15″.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Law 2</title>
    
    <para>There is a point on the Sun's orbit (and on orbits of the other 7 planets) such that when the planet is there
      it is highest above Earth. This point of the Sun's orbit (and so for other planets,
      except for the moon) rotates with constant speed. Its movement every 70 years is approximately 1°.
      This point is called <glossterm linkend="gva-hashemesh">Sun's apogee</glossterm>.
      Its movement in 10 days is one and a half seconds, i.e. 0°0′1″30‴.
      It follows that its movement in 100 days is 0°0′15″.
      Its movement in 1000 days is 0°2′30″.
      Its movement in 10000 days is 0°25′.
      It also follows that its movement in 29 days is 0°0′4″ and a bit more; and its movement in a regular year is 0°0′53″.
    </para>
    
    <para>We already said that the epoch that our calculations start from is beginning of the
      night of the fifth day that is 3rd of Nisan of the year 4938 from the Creation.
      Position of the Sun in its mean movement at the epoch was 7°3′32″ in the constellation of Ram (Tele).
      Position of the Sun's apogee at the epoch was 26°45′8″ in the constellation of Twins.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
