<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Chapter 1</title>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 1</title>
    <para>The months of the year are lunar months, as it is said: "[...] the burnt offering of the month in its month" <footnote>
      <para>Bamidbar 28:14</para>
    </footnote> and it is said: "This month shall be for you the head of the months" <footnote>
      <para>Shemos 12:2</para>
    </footnote>. This is what the sages said:
      "The Holy One, blessed be He, showed to Moshe, in a prophetic vision, the image of the Moon, and said to him:
      '[When] you see [the Moon] like this - sanctify [it].'"<footnote><para>Rosh Hashanah 20b; Menachot 29a</para></footnote>
    </para>
    <para>But the years that we reckon are solar years, as it is said: "Keep the month of aviv [spring]".
      <footnote><para>Dvarim 16</para></footnote>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 2</title>
    <para>By how much is the solar year longer than the lunar year? By approximately 11 days. Therefore, when this excess
      accumulates to around 30 days, or a little less, or a little more, a month is added and the year is made to have
      13 months - which is called a "pregnant" year. [This is done] because it is impossible to have a year of 12 months
      and some days, as it is said: "for the months of the year" - you count the months of the year, but not the days of
      the year.
      <footnote><para>Megilla 5a; Nazir 7a</para></footnote>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 3</title>
    <para>Each month, the moon becomes hidden for about two days, or a little less or more: about one day before its
      conjunction with the sun at the end of the month, and about one day after its conjunction with the sun, and in the
      evening it is sightet in the west. The night when it is sighted in the west after being hidden is the beginning of
      the month. We count 29 days from that day; if the moon is sighted on the 30th night, the 30th day is the first day
      of the [next] month. If it is not sighted, first day of the [next] month is the 31st day, and the 30th day belongs
      to the previous month. On the 31st night, we do not depend on the moon, regardless if it is visible or not, since
      lunar month is never longer than 30 days.</para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 4</title>
    <para>Month of 29 days, [when] the moon was sighted on the 30th night, is called "lacking". If the moon was not
      sighted, and the previous month has 30 days, it is called "pregnant" month, or "full" month.
      The moon sighted on the 30th night is called "moon sighted on time". If it is sighted on the 31st night, but
      not on the 30th night, it is called "moon sighted on the night of pregnancy".</para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 5</title>
    <para>Sighting of the moon is not up to an individual, unlike determination of the Shabbos, where one
      counts 6 days and observes Shabbos on the 7th, but is given to the court. Only when the court sanctifies and
      establishes the day as the beginning of the [new] month does it become the beginning of the [new] month.
      As it is said: "this month shall be for you" - this testimony is entrusted to you.</para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 6</title>
    <para>The court calculates, like the astronomers who know positions of the planets and their movements,
      and look into it until they know if it is possible for the moon to be sighted on time - that is, on the 30th
      night - or not. If they determined that it is possible for it to be sighted, they sit and wait for withnesses
      all day - that is, the 30th day. If the witnesses did come and were examined in accordance with the law, and
      their words were accepted - they sanctify it. If the moon was not sighted and the witnesses did not come,
      they complete the 30 days and the month will be "pregnant". If they found out from calculations that it is
      impossible to sight the moon, they do not sit during the 30th day and do not await the witnesses.
      And if the witnesses did come, it is certain that they are false witnesses or that they saw a likeness of the
      moon in the clouds and not the real moon.</para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 7</title>
    <para>It is a positive commandment of the Torah for the court to calculate and to know whether the moon can
      be sighted or not, and to examine the witnesses before the month is sanctified, and to send [messengers] to
      notify the rest of the people which day is the beginning of the month, so that they know on which day are
      the festivals. As it is said: "which you will call the holy convocations" and as it is said : "keep this
      statute in its time".</para>
  </section>

  <section role = "NotInToc">
    <title>Law 8</title>
    <para>Calculation and establishment of the months and declaration of "pregnant" years is done only in the
      Land of Israel, as it is said: "For out of Zion will come forth Torah, and the word of G-d - from Yerushalaim".
      But, if there was a man great in wisdom, and ordained in the Land of Israel, who came out of the Land, and
      there remains no one equal to him in the Land of Israel, he can calculate and establish month, and declares
      "pregnant" years outside of the Land. If he becomes aware that in the Land of Israel there appeared a man as great
      as him - or, needless to say, greater than him - he is prohibited to establish and to proclaim outside of the Land,
      and if he transgressed and did establish or did proclaim, it is as if he didn't do a thing.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
