<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
>
  <title>Chapter 12</title>

  <section>
    <title>Law 1</title>

    <para>The mean rate of movement of the sun in one day - that is, twenty four hours - is 59′8″.</para>

    <para>For longer periods, (remainder) of the movement in mean lunar longitude is:</para>

    <xi:include href="data:slm-original.xml"/>

    <para>
      And in this way you can calculate it for any number of days and years that you want.
      And so if you want to calculate movement in 2, 3, 4 - up to 10 days - you can do it.
      And so if you want to calculate movement in 20, 30, 40 - up to 100 days - you can do it.
      And it is obvious that once you know the movement in one day.
      Regular lunar year is 354 days.
    </para>

    <para>
      Between two consecutive nights of observation there is 29 full days.
      Between night of observation of a given month and the night of observation of the same month next year
      is in a regular year - or one day more.
      Our goal in all these calculations is solely to determine visibility of the moon.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Law 2</title>

    <para>
      There is a point on the Sun's orbit (and on orbits of the other 7 planets)
      where Sun is the highest above Earth. This point of the Sun's orbit (and so for other planets,
      except for the moon) rotates with constant speed. Movement of this point is approximately
      1° every 70 years. This point is called Sun's apogee (gva hashemesh).
    </para>

    <para>
      We already said that the epoch that our calculations are based on is beginning of the
      night of the fifth day that is 3rd of Nisan of the year 4938 from the Creation.
      And mean longitude of the Sun was at the epoch 7°3′32″ in the zodiac of Ram (tele).
      And apogee of the Sun was 26°45′8″ in the zodiac of Twins.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
