<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xml:base="http://podval.org/docbook/data/"
>
    <title>Lunar Theory</title>

        <section>
            <title>Chapter 14</title>

            <section>
                <title>Law 1: Two Movements of the Moon</title>

                <para>The moon has two mean movements. The moon itself rotates on a small circle
                    that does not surround all of the Earth. Moon's movement on that small circle is
                    called <glossterm linkend="mla-term">mean lunar anomaly</glossterm> (אמצע המסלול). The small circle
                    (epicycle TODO link to Wikipedia) itself rotates on a big circle (deferent TODO link to Wikipedia)
                    that encircles the Earth.
                    The mean movement of the small circle on the big circle that encircles the Earth
                    is called movement of the <glossterm>mean lunar longitude</glossterm> (אמצע הירח). </para>

                <para>Note: The first is "mean" - because it is corrected by the second, giving "true"?
                    Why is the second "mean"? Because of the effects of the sun?</para>
                <para>Note: Wrom what and in which direction are the angles measured?</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 2: Movement in the Mean Lunar Longitude</title>

                <para>
                    Movement in mean lunar longitude in one day is 13°10′35″
                    <footnote><para>This is part of Law 1.</para></footnote>.
                </para>

                <para>For longer periods, (remainder) of the movement in mean lunar longitude is:</para>

                <xi:include href="data:mlm-original.xml"/>

                <para>
                    And in this way you can calculate it for any number of days and years that you want.
                </para>

                <section>
                    <title>Discussion</title>
                    <para>
                        Rambam uses ‘nimzes’ instead of ‘nimzo’ for 10000 days. Also, Rambam says
                        "'ordered' year"; it was rendered as 254 in accordance with Law 12:1.
                    </para>

                    <para> It is not clear how Rambam arrived at the values he gives. When
                        value of the movement in one day given by Rambam is multiplied by 29, 100 etc.,
                        the result is smaller than that of Rambam.
                        The following table compares printed and calculated values:</para>

                    <xi:include href="mlm-calculated.xml"/>

                    <para>
                        Moreover, the value of the movement of the mean lunar longitude in one day given by
                        <biblioref linkend="Almagest"/> IV 3 (H278)
                        (which, rounded to seconds, becomes Rambam's value) is even smaller, so Rambam's
                        numbers can not be explained by performing calculations with the long value from
                        Almagest and then rounding the results.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        From the printed values it is possible to reconstruct the value of the
                        movement in mean lunar longitude in one day that Rambam used to calculate each of them:</para>
                    <!-- TODO
                    <xi:include href="mlm-reconstructed.xml"/>
                    -->

                    <para>
                        Following table compares the printed values with calculations based on the most "precise" reconstructed value - that for 10000 days.
                    </para>

                    <!-- TODO
                    <xi:include href="mlm-recalculated.xml"/>
                    -->

                    <para>
                        Values of the movement in one day apparently used by Rambam, if rounded to the seconds, all give the "official" Rambam's value.
                        Values calculated from the value reconstructed from the printed 10000 days movement, if rounded, produce the values Rambam published -
                        except for 354 days movement, which remains unexplained TODO!
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 3: Movement in the Mean Lunar Anomaly</title>
                <para>
                    Movement in mean lunar anomaly in one day is 13°3′54″.
                </para>
                <para>
                    For longer periods, (remainder) of the movement in mean lunar anomaly is:
                </para>

                <xi:include href="mam-original.xml"/>

                <section>
                    <title>Discussion</title>
                    <para>
                        Rambam says "'ordered' year"; it was rendered as 254 in accordance with see Law 12:1.
                        Also, this value is actually given in Law 4.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        It is not clear how Rambam obtained the values he gives.
                        When value of the movement in one day given by Rambam is
                        multiplied by 29, 100 etc., the result is bigger than what Rambam says!
                        The following table compares printed and calculated values:
                    </para>
                
                    <xi:include href="mam-calculated.xml"/>

                    <para>
                        Although the value of the movement of the mean lunar anomaly in one day given by
                        <biblioref linkend="Almagest"/> IV 3 (H278)
                        (which, rounded to seconds, becomes Rambam's value) is smaller, it is not small enough,
                        and Rambam's
                        numbers can not be explained by performing calculations with the long value from
                        Almagest and then rounding the results (TODO: table).
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        From the printed values it is possible to reconstruct the value of the
                        movement in mean lunar anomaly in one day that Rambam used to calculate each of them:</para>
                    <!-- TODO
                    <xi:include href="mam-reconstructed.xml"/>
                    -->

                    <para>
                        Following table compares the printed values with calculations based on the most "precise" reconstructed value - that for 10000 days.
                    </para>

                    <!-- TODO
                    <xi:include href="mam-recalculated.xml"/>
                    -->

                    <para>
                        Values of the movement in one day apparently used by Rambam, if rounded to the seconds, all give the "official" Rambam's value.
                        Values calculated from the value reconstructed from the printed 10000 days movement, if rounded, produce the values Rambam published -
                        except for 354 days movement, which remains unexplained TODO!
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        Here, everything is worse than in 14:2 TODO!!!
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 4: Position of the Moon on the Epoch</title>

                <para>
                    In the beginning of the night to Thursday that is the epoch (TODO measured from what? Chapter 11?) [TODO: link to definition]
                    for these calculations, mean lunar longitude was 1°14′43″ into the constellation of Ram.
                    And mean lunar anomaly on the epoch was 84°28′42″.
                    Now that you know rate of movement in the mean lunar longitude and its value on the epoch
                    to which you add, you'll calculate mean lunar longitude on any day that you want the same
                    way as you did for the mean solar longitude. TODO: reference
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 5,6: Mean Lunar Longitude at Observation Time</title>

                <para> After you calculate mean lunar longitude at the
                    beginning of the night that you want, contemplate the sun (TODO: longitude?) and figure out which
                    constellation (zodiac) is it in <footnote><para>This is part of Law 4.</para></footnote>.
                    [This is the correction of the mean lunar longitude depending on
                    the mean solar longitude:]
                </para>

                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols="4">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Solar Longitude on the Zodiac</entry>
                                <entry>from</entry>
                                <entry>to, not including<footnote><para>My understanding of the word usage in the original.</para></footnote></entry>
                                <entry>Lunar longitude correction</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>middle of Pisces-middle of Taurus
                                    <footnote><para>See Chapter 11, Law 7 on the start of Jewish Zodiac. (TODO reference)</para></footnote>
                                </entry>
                                <entry>315°</entry>
                                <entry>15°</entry>
                                <entry>0°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>middle of Taurus-beginning of Gemini</entry>
                                <entry>15°</entry>
                                <entry>30°</entry>
                                <entry>0°15′</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>beginning of Gemini-beginning of Leo</entry>
                                <entry>30°</entry>
                                <entry>90°</entry>
                                <entry>0°15′</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>beginning of Leo-middle of Virgo</entry>
                                <entry>90°</entry>
                                <entry>135°</entry>
                                <entry>0°15′</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>middle of Virgo-middle of Libra</entry>
                                <entry>135°</entry>
                                <entry>165°</entry>
                                <entry>0°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>middle of Libra-beginning of Sagittarius</entry>
                                <entry>165°</entry>
                                <entry>210°</entry>
                                <entry>-0°15′</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>beginning of Sagittarius-beginning of Aquarius</entry>
                                <entry>210°</entry>
                                <entry>270°</entry>
                                <entry>-0°30′</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>beginning of Aquarius-middle of Pisces</entry>
                                <entry>270°</entry>
                                <entry>315°</entry>
                                <entry>-0°15′</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>

                <para>
                    TODO: Compare with 11:9, about Dli... Something is off!
                </para>

                <para>
                    The value of mean [lunar longitude]
                    after you add to it or subtract from it or leave it as
                    it is - that is mean lunar longitude approximately a third of an hour after sunset on the
                    date you are calculating it for. And this is what is called
                    <glossterm>mean lunar longitude at observation time</glossterm>.
                    <footnote><para>This is Law 6.</para></footnote>
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Chapter 15</title>

            <section>
                <title>Law 1: Doubled Distance</title>

                <para>
                    To find true lunar longitude (הירח האמיתי) on a specific day:
                    First, calculate mean lunar longitude during observation time of the desired night.
                    Also, calculate mean lunar anomaly and mean solar longitude for the same time.
                    Then, subtract mean solar longitude from the mean lunar longitude and double the result.
                    This value is called <glossterm>doubled distance</glossterm> (מרחק הכפול).
                </para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 2,3: Corrected Mean Anomaly (Elongation (TODO: ?))</title>

                <para>
                    We already stipulated that all the calculations in these chapters are for one purpose only:
                    to know if the moon is visible. And it is not possible for this double distance during the night of
                    observation when the moon is indeed visible to be outside of the interval from 5° to 62°.
                    It cannot be more - nor less.
                    <footnote><para>This is Law 2.</para></footnote>
                </para>

                <para> A correction that depends on the doubled distance is added to the mean lunar
                    anomaly, giving  <glossterm>corrected lunar anomaly</glossterm> (מסלול הנכון): </para>

                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols="2">
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>doubled distance</entry>
                                <entry>correction of the mean anomaly</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>~5°</entry>
                                <entry>0°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>6°-11°</entry>
                                <entry>1°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>12°-18°</entry>
                                <entry>2°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>19°-24°</entry>
                                <entry>3°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>25°-31°</entry>
                                <entry>4°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>32°-38°</entry>
                                <entry>5°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>39°-45°</entry>
                                <entry>6°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>46°-51°</entry>
                                <entry>7°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>52°-59°</entry>
                                <entry>8°</entry>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <entry>60°-63°</entry>
                                <entry>9°</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>

                <section>
                    <title>Discussion</title>
                    <para>
                        Rambam does not describe the model behind this correction.
                        Because the models Rambam did describe until now are the same
                        as Almagest's models
                        (including numerical parameters), and because this correction
                        is determined by the (doubled)
                        sun-moon elongation, just like Almagest's "improved" model of
                        the moon ("the crank"),
                        I assume that that model was used to calculate this correction.
                        TODO: describe the model!
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        TODO: Derive the formula! Make the diagram!
                        TODO: How come the fact that sun and moon move in different
                        plains does not affect this calculation?
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        It seems that Rambam treats "the crank" as just a calculation
                        device - otherwise,
                        table giving visible anomaly from the corrected anomaly should
                        take into account changes in the
                        earth-moon distance depending on the elongation - and it does not!
                        Maybe that is why he does not describe the model behind this correction.
                        And maybe this is why Rambam reiterates - in Law 2 - that only the observability of the new moon
                        needs to be calculated correctly.
                        TODO: How does Almagest calculate visible anomaly?
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 4,5,6: True Lunar Longitude</title>

                <para xml:id="l15-4"> Then, see how many degrees is corrected lunar anomaly. If it
                    is less than 180°, subtract visible anomaly of this corrected anomaly from the
                    mean lunar longitude the observation time. And if corrected lunar anomaly is
                    more than 180° but less than 360°, add visible anomaly of this corrected anomaly
                    to the mean lunar longitude the observation time. And mean lunar longitude after
                    you add to it or subtract from it is the
                    <glossterm>true lunar longitude at the observation time</glossterm>.
                    <footnote><para>This is Law 4.</para></footnote>
                </para>

                <para xml:id="l15-5">
                    If the corrected anomaly is 180° or 360°, there is no visible anomaly,
                    so mean lunar longitude at observation time is also true longitude.
                    <footnote><para>This is Law 5.</para></footnote>
                </para>

                <para xml:id="l15-6">
                    What is the value of the visible
                    anomaly for a given value of the corrected anomaly?
                </para>

                <!-- TODO
                <xi:include href="mva-original.xml"/>
                -->

                <section>
                    <title>Discussion</title>
                    <para> Formulae: <equation>
                        <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" display="block">
                            <!-- Browsers (and MathJax) do not support Content MathML, so I have to settle for presentation... -->
                            <!-- TODO doesn't show in the DocBook PDF! -->
                            <mrow>
                                <msup>
                                    <mi>tan</mi>
                                    <mrow>
                                        <mo>-</mo>
                                        <mn>1</mn>
                                    </mrow>
                                </msup>
                                <mo>(</mo>
                                <mfrac>
                                    <mrow>
                                        <mi>sin</mi>
                                        <mi>α</mi>
                                    </mrow>
                                    <mrow>
                                        <mi>cos</mi>
                                        <mi>α</mi>
                                        <mo>+</mo>
                                        <mi>ε</mi>
                                    </mrow>
                                </mfrac>
                                <mo>)</mo>
                            </mrow>
                        </math>
                    </equation> R - radius of the big circle; r - radius of the small circle; e
                        = R/r. A little trigonometry, and we get: visible anomaly =
                        arctg(sin(corrected anomaly)/(cos(corrected anomaly) + e)) and: e =
                        ctg(visible anomaly)*sin(corrected anomaly) - cos(corrected anomaly) </para>
                
                    <para>TODO: Make the diagram! Here?</para>

                    <para>
                        It is clear that values for 150° and 170° are misprinted: they are bigger than the one before them
                        when they should be smaller. Value for 120° is also misprinted, but it is less obvious.
                    </para>
                
                    <para>
                        Calculations show that for the precision up to a minute,
                        it is sufficient to know e to up to the second
                        digit after the dot.
                        Below, a column giving the value of e was added to the table.
                        Look at the value of e, and the misprints become obvious:
                        value of e for them is way out of range it is in
                        for the rest of them.
                    </para>
                    <!-- TODO
                    <xi:include href="mva-withe.xml"/>
                    -->
                    
                    <para>
                        TODO Range of e - graph. Range of possible values for each based on the range of e.
                        This is transcription error: one letter; extra word... Probable correct values.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        This is how different sources treat the often misprinted values:
                    </para>
                
                    <informaltable frame="all">
                        <tgroup cols="4">
                            <thead>
                                <row>
                                    <entry>Edition</entry>
                                    <entry>120°</entry>
                                    <entry>150°</entry>
                                    <entry>170°</entry>
                                </row>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Vilno"/></entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Eshkol"/></entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="LaAm"/></entry>
                                    <entry>corrected in the notes</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Kapach"/>
                                        <footnote>
                                            <para>
                                                It is not clear how did authoritative Yemenite texts acquire the same misprints
                                                as in the ashkenazic editions.
                                            </para>
                                        </footnote>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>corrected in the notes</entry>
                                    <entry>corrected in the notes</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Bluming"/></entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>corrected in the notes</entry>
                                    <entry>corrected in the notes</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Frenkel"/></entry>
                                    <entry>correct and noted</entry>
                                    <entry>correct and noted</entry>
                                    <entry>correct and noted</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Keller"/></entry>
                                    <entry>not given</entry>
                                    <entry>not given</entry>
                                    <entry>not given</entry>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <entry><biblioref linkend="Losh"/>
                                        <footnote>
                                            <para>
                                                Reprints the text and does not correct any of the misprints - surpising for a textbook
                                                on the subject (even introductory).
                                                TODO: Link to the scans of the appropriate pages - with the stuff highlighted.
                                            </para>
                                        </footnote>
                                    </entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                    <entry>incorrect</entry>
                                </row>
                            </tbody>
                        </tgroup>
                    </informaltable>
                </section>                    
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Law 7,8,9:</title>
                <para>
                    TODO!!!
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
