<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="research-questions" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Research Questions (and TODOs)</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Fixed Calendar</title>
    
    <section>
      <title>New moon from 6:7</title>
      
      <para>Rambam mentiones Nisan conjunction on Sunday, 5 hours and 107 units parts after sunrise.
        He doesn't give the year, and there seems to be no such year...</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>RoshHaShono corrections</title>
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>are there meaningful names for the corrections?</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>are corrections explained by the desire to not have Yom Kippur on Sunday etc.?</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>calculate third correction from the maximum length of a year and the first correction</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>KH 7:8 says that postponement of RoshHaShonoh is done to align the calendar better
          with the true molad; analyze the statistics of distances between mean and true molad
          and RoshHashono.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>There is an <ulink
        url="https://he.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D7%9E%D7%97%D7%9C%D7%95%D7%A7%D7%AA_%D7%A8%D7%91_%D7%A1%D7%A2%D7%93%D7%99%D7%94_%D7%92%D7%90%D7%95%D7%9F_%D7%95%D7%91%D7%9F_%D7%9E%D7%90%D7%99%D7%A8">
        argument</ulink> concerning some of the Rosh Hashono delays involving r. Saadia Gaon:

        Спор о размерах "старого молада", когда он отодвигает Рош ашана на следующий день.
        По нашей шите от Расага и дальше - 18 часов
        По шите Аарона Бен Меира - 18 часов и 642/1080 частей часа</para>
      
      <para>make possible calculating the calendar according to the other opinion and compare the results.</para>
      
      <para>Молад года творения человека выходит в пятницу.
        Это и было Рош а-Шана второго года, ведь тогда принцип ли аду Рош не применялся.
        Тогда понятней спор Рамбама и Райвада о причине сдвига Рош а-Шана ло аду.
        Рамбама настаивает, что оно нужно для подсчёта по кибуц эмцаи,
        а Райвад на него из Талмуда возмущается.
        Теоретически можно сделать календарь на время до установления календаря без сдвига Рош а-Шана.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Sun Cycle</title>
      
      <para>Where and when was the Sun created?
        Compare with Rambam's epoch from the astronomical calendar.
        Where and how is date of birchat hachamo defined?
        How would it look according to the other opinion?</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Seasons</title>
      
      <para>Rav Ada's tkufos started a week later than Shmuel's! Isn't it readily observable?
        Analyze the difference in historic periods...</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>Astronomical Calendar</title>
    
    <section>
      <title>Epoch</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>when was the Sun created?</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>introduce "creation" epoch.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>compare calculations based on it and on the Rambam's epoch.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>make possible calculations for a Moment, not just a Day (at least for the sun);</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Math.findZero()</title>
      <para>Finish and test the code; use two separate lengths (precisions)?</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Seasons</title>
      <para>calculate true seasons in SeasonsAstronomical;
        KH 10:7 says that real vernal equinox is approximately two days before the mean one; add a test.</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Exactification</title>
      <para>Tzikuni gives the algorithm of such reconstruction:
        add to the remainder as many times 360 as there were full rotations in given time period,
        and then divide... find the page for exact reference;
        use it to calculate intervals for Rambam's values of the angular velocities</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Angular movement for 29 days</title>
      
      <para>Are Rambam's values reconstructible if value for 29 days is calculated as 3*10-1, not 2*10+9?
        For any tables other than SunLongitudeMean?</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Angular speeds from periods</title>
      
      <para>Convert each year length mentioned in the fixed calendar to angular speed.
        Angular speed of the moon = 360 / (1/tropical month + 1/solar year).
        Moon.meanLunarPeriod - what is it called? Tropical?</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Distance between the mean and true new moons</title>
      
      <para>KH 5:1-2 says that the distance is no more than a day.
        Calculate this difference for all months;
        Rambam's epoch - two days after molad?! (Petya Ofman).</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Day of sighting</title>
      
      <para>How to find the day of sighting given a month?</para></section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Schedule</title>
    
    <section>
      <title>Shulchan Aruch</title>
      <para>Magen Avraham 428:4 (6): When Pesach falls on Shabbat, so that residents of the Land of Israel
        read Shmini on the Shabbat following it, there are those that split Tazria and Metzora,
        and there are those that split Behar and Bechukotai, and if the year is leap, they split
        Matot and Masai.</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Baladi (Yemenite)</title>
      <para>instead of Matot and Masai combine Chukat and Balak</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Daradaim</title>
      <para>(following Rabbi Saadia Gaon): instead of combining Matot and Masai,
        add to Korach Chukat to 20:21, and next Shabbos read the rest of Chukkat and Balak</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>3 small aliyot</title>
      <para>for 2/5/Shabbos day: look into and implement differences in customs</para></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Проблемы календаря, который устанавливался по свидетельствам наблюдения новой луны.</title>
      <para>Отличается от расчитанного:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>основан не на среднем движении солнца и луны, поэтому к молад надо делать поправку, но не путем отодвигания Рош
          а-шана, а методами последних глав Кидуш а-ходеш</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>другой порядок високосных и простых лет</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>другой порядок полных и неполных месяцев</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>возможно ли рассчитать по Рамбаму начало месяцев по этим принципам и сравнить с завиксированныму в традиции датами
          и днями недели?</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Пример: выход из Египта - 15 день от освящения месяца, четверг</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Год рождения Моше: спор был ли год високосным или простым. Шита Ребе - год был високосным.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></section>
    
    <section>
      <title>3-year cycle</title>
      <para>Is anybody orthodox completing Torah cycle in three years?
        If yes, maybe we should generate that schedule too.
        There is a <ulink url="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://faculty.biu.ac.il/~ofery/papers/haftarot3.pdf">list of Haftarot</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Functionality and Integrations</title>

    <section>
      <title>Zmanim</title>

      <para>There is an Android application; it references some kind of an "engine".</para>

      <para>
        Raw data for the hazot calculations is obtainable from the
        <ulink url="http://www.usno.navy.mil/USNO/astronomical-applications/data-services/rs-one-year-us">Naval Oceanography Portal</ulink>.

        There it is produced in accordance with the algorithm described in the Meese's book, I think...
        There is <ulink url="http://www.timeanddate.com/worldclock/sunrise.html">another source of data</ulink>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Joda Time</title>
      As a good open-source citizen I probably should integrate my implementation of the Jewish calendar into
      <ulink url="http://joda-time.sourceforge.net/">Joda Time</ulink> or <ulink url="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=310">JSR 130</ulink>
      (although the latter is inactive, the article
      <ulink url="http://today.java.net/pub/a/today/2008/09/18/jsr-310-new-java-date-time-api.html">New Java Date and Time API</ulink> notwithstanding).
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Google Calendar Integration</title>

      <para>It'd be nice to integrate with the Google Calendar:

        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ICalendar">iCalendar</ulink>
        <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2445">iCalendar RFC</ulink>
        <ulink url="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-calsify-rfc2445bis-08">Revised iCalendar RFC</ulink>
        <ulink url="http://ical4j.sourceforge.net/introduction.html">iCal4j</ulink>
        <ulink url="http://www.google.com/support/calendar/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=48526">Publish web content events in iCalendar format</ulink>
        <ulink url="http://code.google.com/apis/gdata/client-java.html">GData Java library</ulink>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
