<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="solar-theory" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Solar Theory</title>

  <section xml:id="solar-model">
    <title>Model (TODO)</title>
    <para>Figure out from the text directions of Sun's movements and what are the position angles from (look at the
      parallax correction stuff: subtract mean apogee from the mean Sun...).</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="exactification">
    <title>Exactification (TODO)</title>
    <para> It is not clear how Rambam arrived at the values he gives. When value of the movement in one day given by
      Rambam is multiplied by 29, 100 etc., the result is smaller than that of Rambam. The following table compares
      printed and calculated values: TODO</para>
    <para> Although the value of the movement of the mean solar longitude in one day given by <biblioref
        linkend="Almagest"/> III 1 (H209) (which, rounded to seconds, becomes Rambam's value) is bigger, it is not big
      enough, and Rambam's numbers (for more than 10 days) can not be explained by performing calculations with the long
      value from Almagest and then rounding the results to the precision of the Rambam's values.</para>
    <para>
      <biblioref linkend="Tzikuni"/> (TODO p. XXX) gives the algorithm of such reconstruction: add to the remainder as
      many times 360 as there were full rotations in given time period, and then divide. It also gives a value
      reconstructed from the printed values for 10,000, 1000 and 100 days: 59′8.33″, or 0.9856472 degrees, and the
      current "scientific" value of 0.9856473 degrees. It seems that origins of the Rambam's value were questioned by
      his commentators, including "Pirush". Value that can be derived from the tradition that 19 years = 6939 days 16
      hours and 595 parts is 0.9856348. </para>
    <para>This algorithm can be modified to produce an interval of possible values, taking into account precision of the
      numbers.</para>
    <para> From the printed values it is possible to reconstruct the value of the movement in mean solar longitude in
      one day that Rambam used to calculate each of them:</para>
    <para>Use it to calculate intervals for Rambam's values of the angular velocities.</para>
    <para><biblioref linkend="Tzikuni"/> quotes Rambam's value for 354 days as 348°55′15″, but calculated value as
      348°55′9″, and notes that this "requires a little thought".</para>
  </section>

  <section  xml:id="solar-movement-29">
    <title>Angular movement for 29 days (TODO)</title>
    <para>Are Rambam's values reconstructible if value for 29 days is calculated as 3*10-1, not 2*10+9? For any tables
      other than SunLongitudeMean?</para>
    <para> Values of the movement in one day apparently used by Rambam, if rounded to the seconds, give the "official"
      Rambam's value. Values calculated from the value reconstructed from the printed 10000 days movement, if rounded,
      produce the values Rambam published - except for 29 days, 354 days, and 10000 days which we use to calculate the
      exact value that Rambam used! TODO! </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="zeros">
    <title>Zeros (TODO)</title>
    <para>Math.findZero(): Finish and test the code; use two separate lengths (precisions)?</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sun-precise">
    <title>Sun for a precise time (TODO)</title>
    <para>make possible calculations for a Moment, not just a Day (at least for the sun);</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sun-creation">
    <title>Sun at Creation (TODO)</title>
    <para>Where and when was the Sun created? (Birchat Hachamo is on a different opinion.) Does it let us get more
      precise values of Sun's angular velocities?</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="true-seasons">
    <title>True seasons (TODO)</title>
    <para>calculate true seasons in SeasonsAstronomical; KH 10:7 says that real vernal equinox is approximately two days
      before the mean one; add a test.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="year-lengths">
    <title>Year lengths (TODO)</title>
    <para>Convert each year length mentioned in the fixed calendar to angular speed.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
