<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.oxygenxml.com/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/dbmathmlsvg.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <title>Solar Theory</title>
    
    <section>
        <title>Chapter 12</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 1</title>
            
            <para>
                Mean movement of the Sun in one day (that is, twenty four hours) is 59′8″.
                
            </para>
            
            <para>For longer periods, (remainder) of the movement in mean lunar longitude is:</para>
            
            <xi:include href="../../../target/tables/sml-original.xml"/>
            
            <para>
                And in this way you can calculate it for any number of days and years that you want.
                And so if you want to calculate movement in 2, 3, 4 - up to 10 days - you can do it.
                And so if you want to calculate movement in 20, 30, 40 - up to 100 days - you can do it.
                And it is obvious that once you know the movement in one day.
                Regular lunar year is 354 days.
            </para>
            
            <para>
                Between two consecutive nights of observation there is 29 full days.
                Between night of observation of a given month and the night of observation of the same month next year
                is in a regular year - or one day more.
                Our goal in all these calculations is solely to determine visibility of the moon.
            </para>

            <section>
                <title>Discussion</title>
 
                <para> It is not clear how Rambam arrived at the values he gives. When value of the
                    movement in one day given by Rambam is multiplied by 29, 100 etc., the result is
                    smaller than that of Rambam. The following table compares printed and calculated
                    values:</para>

                <xi:include href="../../../target/tables/sml-calculated.xml"/>

                <para> Although the value of the movement of the mean solar longitude in one day
                    given by <biblioref linkend="Almagest"/> III 1 (H209) (which, rounded to
                    seconds, becomes Rambam's value) is bigger, it is not big enough, and Rambam's
                    numbers (for more than 10 days) can not be explained by performing calculations
                    with the long value from Almagest and then rounding the results. </para>
                
                <xi:include href="../../../target/tables/sml-almagest.xml"/>

                <para>
                    From the printed values it is possible to reconstruct the value of the
                    movement in mean solar longitude in one day that Rambam used to calculate each of them:</para>
                
                <xi:include href="../../../target/tables/sml-reconstructed.xml"/>
                
                <para>
                    Following table compares the printed values with calculations based on the most "precise" reconstructed value - that for 10000 days.
                </para>
                
                <xi:include href="../../../target/tables/sml-recalculated.xml"/>
                <xi:include href="../../../target/tables/sml-recalculated10.xml"/>
                
                <para> Values of the movement in one day apparently used by Rambam, if rounded to
                    the seconds, give the "official" Rambam's value. Values calculated from the
                    value reconstructed from the printed 10000 days movement, if rounded, produce
                    the values Rambam published - except for 29 days, 354 days, and 10000 days which
                    we use to calculate the exact value that Rambam used! TODO! </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 2</title>
            
            <para>
                There is a point on the Sun's orbit (and on orbits of the other 7 planets)
                where Sun is the highest above Earth. This point of the Sun's orbit (and so for other planets,
                except for the moon) rotates with constant speed. Movement of this point is approximately
                1° every 70 years. This point is called Sun's apogee (gva hashemesh).
            </para>
            
            <para>
                We already said that the epoch that our calculations are based on is beginning of the
                night of the fifth day that is 3rd of Nisan of the year 4938 from the Creation.
                And mean longitude of the Sun was at the epoch 7°3′32″ in the constelation of Ram (tele).
                And apogee of the Sun was 26°45′8″ in the constellation of Twins.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Chapter 13</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 1</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 2</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 3</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 4</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 5</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 6</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 7</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 8</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 9</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 10</title>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Law 11</title>
        </section>
    </section>
</section>
