<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xml:id="solar-theory"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Solar Theory</title>

  <section>
    <title>Discussion: Chapter 12, Law 1</title>

    <para> It is not clear how Rambam arrived at the values he gives. When value of the
      movement in one day given by Rambam is multiplied by 29, 100 etc., the result is
      smaller than that of Rambam. The following table compares printed and calculated
      values:</para>

    <xi:include href="data:slm-calculated.xml"/>

    <para> Although the value of the movement of the mean solar longitude in one day
      given by <biblioref linkend="Almagest"/> III 1 (H209) (which, rounded to
      seconds, becomes Rambam's value) is bigger, it is not big enough, and Rambam's
      numbers (for more than 10 days) can not be explained by performing calculations
      with the long value from Almagest and then rounding the results to the precision
      of the Rambam's values. </para>

    <xi:include href="data:/slm-almagest.xml"/>

    <para>
      From the printed values it is possible to reconstruct the value of the
      movement in mean solar longitude in one day that Rambam used to calculate each of them:</para>
    <!-- TODO
    <xi:include href="slm-reconstructed.xml"/>
    -->

    <para>
      <biblioref linkend="Tzikuni"/> (p. XXX) gives the algorithm of such reconstruction: add to the
      remainder as many times 360 as there were full rotations in given time period, and then divide.
      It also gives a value reconstructed from the printed values for 10,000, 1000 and 100 days: 59′8.33″,
      or 0.9856472 degrees, and the current "scientific" value of 0.9856473 degrees. It seems that origins
      of the Rambam's value were questioned by his commentators, including "Pirush". Value that can be
      derived from the tradition that 19 years = 6939 days 16 hours and 595 parts is 0.9856348. This
      algorithm can be modified to produce an interval of possible values, taking into account precision
      of the numbers.</para>

    <para>
      Following table compares the printed values with calculations based on the most "precise"
      reconstructed value - that for 10000 days.
    </para>

    <!-- TODO the intervals
    <xi:include href="slm-recalculated.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="slm-recalculated10.xml"/>
    -->

    <para> Values of the movement in one day apparently used by Rambam, if rounded to
      the seconds, give the "official" Rambam's value. Values calculated from the
      value reconstructed from the printed 10000 days movement, if rounded, produce
      the values Rambam published - except for 29 days, 354 days, and 10000 days which
      we use to calculate the exact value that Rambam used! TODO! </para>

    <para><biblioref linkend="Tzikuni"/> quotes Rambam's value for 354 days as 348°55′15″, but calculated value
      as 348°55′9″, and notes that this "requires a little thought".</para>
  </section>
</section>
